check out all these before and after
pictures now say the person on the left
hired me in each of these scenarios and
i said guess what
you're gonna train really hard for the
next couple years and you're not gonna
lose any weight
your weight's gonna stay the same
chances are every one of these people
would have fired me
because in their heads they need to lose
weight they need to cut their calories
they need to starve themselves and do
tons of cardio to lean out when in
actuality they didn't change their
calories they ate at a maintenance
increase their strength and look at the
results this my friends
is recomping at its finest in this video
i'm going to teach you about recomping
and it would make the case that a lot of
people should in fact just be recomping
you'll need to be on an endless bulky
and cutting cycle just get to a
comfortable body weight where you're
okay with the way you look and then try
to get stronger over time
take one so there's three typical
scenarios in strength training
scenario one you want to gain weight you
got to eat more calories
you're bulking scenario two you want to
lose weight so you consume
less calories you're cutting and a much
lesser known scenario
is where you just want to stay the same
weight but improve your body composition
well that's called recomping now the
reason i'm making this video is because
scenario one and two are so much more
popular than scenario three and in
reality they should all be equal
they're all equally viable strategies
depending on the goal of the lifter
in high school when i first started
lifting i was so skinny i was a scrawny
little
sophomore in high school i weighed like
135 pounds
over the next two years i grew eight
inches and gained 70 pounds
through lifting weights and mainly
through eating more i was so active back
then i had to stuff my face in order to
gain weight
smells chocolatey
now eat it you know i'd make these
get big shakes at night where i just
throw everything into a blender
and then drink as much as i could before
i went to sleep and then i'd wake up in
the middle of night to pee
and i'd finish the rest of it off that
was an extra 1500 calories that i
consumed while most people were sleeping
now eventually i got to a point where i
was
chunky you know i had a belly and at
first it was like this is kind of cool
i'm not skinny anymore people are making
fun of me for for being fat
and at least i'm not skinny and then i
realize i don't like this either
so i chilled out on the junk food but i
actually didn't lose weight
i just kept lifting weights hard and
eventually i lost my belly well what
happened i recommend now these days i
hover at around 250 pounds
i'm not very lean but when i want to be
lean i lose 15 pounds i get down to
about 235
i have abs again therefore i'm cutting
so there exists this
huge misconception out there that you
you should always be either in a bulking
phase or a cutting phase that that's
going to maximize your results
now here's the theoretical rationale you
don't want your body fat too low that's
not good for gaining muscle
and so you need to get your body fat
levels up to optimal levels
and this will put you in a better state
for building muscle so during the
bulking phase you built as much muscle
as possible
then you do say uh eight week cutting
phase
where you try to shut off the fat and
hold on to as much muscle as possible
but once you cut down you're again too
lean for building muscles so you bulk up
again
here's the problem with that most people
never get too lean
to where they can't optimally build
muscle i'm not aware of any research on
this topic and it probably depends on
the individual
but i would think that below 10 body fat
for men and probably below 15
body fat for women would not lend
themselves to optimal muscle building
environments you know optimal
hormonal mulu with inside the body
that's conducive to building muscle
so let's forget about bodybuilding okay
because that's what bodybuilders do and
it works well
we don't need to base what we do with
the average person you know
the the majority of the population on
what bodybuilders do
because bodybuilders are the genetic
elite who also happen to be taking the
most amount of gear
that's it we're carter
they're not representative of joe and
jane public so here's this scenario most
of my female clients come to me
you know they tend to look pretty good
already say the woman is five foot seven
and weighs 135.
she will come to me and say i want to
lose fat you know i want to get lean but
here's the deal
if i just said okay i'm gonna put you on
a big deficit i'm gonna give you a ton
of cardio and you're gonna lose 15
pounds you know you're gonna drop to 120
in the next two months
she would not end up liking the way she
looked she wouldn't be satisfied once
she got there
she'd get to 120 and she'd still have
too much body fat and too little shape
for her liking i mean that's based on my
experience as a trainer so
if i would tell the client at that point
in time you know what
you're gonna lift with me for the whole
year and you're not gonna change
in body weight whatsoever you're gonna
stay 135 the whole time they'd probably
walk
out the door and wouldn't come back
because their minds couldn't envision
what they were going to look like
one year later when they were much
stronger but that tends to be what
happens
they'll stay 135 the whole year they
tend to eat the right amount of calories
i'll just make sure that they're eating
enough protein you know
around one gram per pound of body weight
per day so i try to say try to eat you
know
between 120 and 135 grams of protein a
day
you know they might have to drink a whey
protein shake or supplement
or just make sure they're eating four
meals with protein per day
but i typically won't adjust their
calories i won't even give them
instructions to eat less or more
so i just address the protein and then i
get them stronger
so throughout the year you know say they
come to me relatively untrained
maybe they start out hip thrusting 95
pounds they start off squatting 65
pounds to parallel
you know they start off deadlifting like
95 pounds with bumper plates
they can't do a chin up they might start
off bench pressing the bar
for like 12 reps and if i give a
military press with the bar they might
struggle to just get a couple reps
12 months later they're hip thrusting
315 pounds for 15 reps
they're squatting 175 for 5. they're
lifting 225 for five they can do five
chin ups and they can bust out 20 reps
in the military press with the bar
it's going to require a lot more muscle
to carry out those feets of strength
so if they packed on all that muscle but
they didn't change on the scale
you know their body weight stayed the
same and they packed down say eight
pounds of muscle throughout the year
that would mean that they lost eight
pounds of fat you know they
simultaneously
gained muscle and lost fat and this
might translate to like a five or six
percent reduction in body fat percentage
you know let's say they start off at 21
body fat now maybe they're 15
body fat and that muscle has curve that
muscle
is packed on in places where you want it
you know your
delts your glutes you know your nice
shapely leg muscles
and the fat is typically lost off the
problem areas you know
around the midsection the thighs the
love handles
the back of the arms now you're left
with a leaner appearance
you look very athletic and strong and
most importantly you're a smaller
version of your former self
at equal weights muscle takes up around
15 to 20 percent less space than fat
so picture like a human body but like a
an anatomy chart you know muscular
anatomy chart and the muscles are in red
and the fat is in yellow okay and then
you take
eight more pounds of the red and place
them in strategic areas
and you take away eight pounds of the
yellow and you take them off of the
problem areas
and you'll have to take off more yellow
than red
because again fat is less dense than
muscle so it takes up more space
and you're left with a big visual change
it's commonly said
in our industry that the only people who
can successfully recomp
are either a total beginners b people
returning from a long layoff of lifting
you know
because of muscle memory you know say
you took the last six months off lifting
well yeah you can recomp quickly because
of muscle memory and see
people taking anabolic steroids but in
my experience i take even very advanced
lifters who have
good physiques and are very strong and i
recomp them when they start training
with me and when they start training
with me they recomp
they get leaner they get stronger they
gain muscle they lose fat they get
leaner
another category that isn't mentioned is
people who tend to get really focused
you know say they have a wedding coming
up or or a photo shoot or a competition
or like me a 40th birthday where i just
said you know what
i'm making lifting my number one goal i
recompt at age 39
even though i had been lifting since i
was 15. 24 years into lifting
i was still able to recomp because i
made it my number one focus
so so far this has all been theoretical
but let me show you some anecdotes from
just this year in my gym
i've been talking about recomping for
quite some time now for like the past
five years or so i've really been
preaching the benefits of recomping but
i just posted this
on june 12th and this is my client
ashley hodge
two years ago she weighed 135 pounds and
today she weighs 135 pounds during that
time her squat went from 200 to 250
pounds so she put 50 pounds on her squat
bench went from 140 pounds to 170 pounds
so she put 30 pounds on her bench
her deadlift went from 275 pounds to 405
pounds so she put 130 pounds on her
deadlift
military press went from 85 pounds to
101 pounds so she put on 16 pounds on
her one rep max military press
her max chin went from 25 pound extra
weight
to 75 pounds so she put 50 pounds on her
weighted chin
and her max hip thrust was 365 pounds
now it's 600 pounds so that's 245 pounds
on her hip thrust in two years
all right so what does this look like
see for yourself
i mean these changes are incredible now
let's see what ashley looks like trying
on her pair of jeans from two years ago
as you can see look at that gap these
used to fit her fine
you see this crazy gap thereby
demonstrating
that recomping makes you smaller i'm
going to say two different statements
that you need to think about these okay
you need to let this sink in the
smallest you can possibly be
at any given body weight is when you're
the strongest you can possibly be
at that body weight put another way no
matter what weight you are
the stronger you are the smaller you'll
be for example
right now i'm 250 pounds if i could
squat
100 more pounds bench press 100 more
pounds
deadlift 100 more pounds i would have to
have more muscle on me
but i'm 250 pounds so i'd have to have
less fat i would be a
smaller version of myself even at 250
pounds well what if i weighed 200 pounds
again the stronger i was at 200 pounds
the leaner and smaller overall i'd be
so strength training makes you smaller
at any given body weight i want to tell
you a funny little story about my client
alexis
on may 9th i posted this video showing
off her victory
she compete in bikini she won first in
her class in the final
2.5 weeks of prep she stayed the same
body weight you know she stayed 98
pounds
so we didn't lose any weight from 2.5
weeks out
to the day of the show but i realized
that she was really weak
you know she hadn't been pushing herself
as hard as she does when i'm there
so i went back to san diego and busted
her butt for two and a half weeks
you know she ended up setting pr's on
everything during those two and a half
weeks she went from hip thrusting 225
for three
to 275 for five but everything went up
her chin ups her military price her
bench press her squats her stiff leg
deadlifts
everything went up so during those 2.5
weeks she lost
1.5 inches on her thighs this was just
two and a half weeks
and the difference was very noticeable
so recomping can happen
rather quickly if you do it right and
there are numerous examples for example
here's something i posted three days ago
on june 21st
this is my booty by brett member sydney
squats she weighs 125 pounds
in both picks the left and the right
what happened during that time period
she got way stronger she trains really
hard
she's gotten very strong and you can see
the increased confidence so how many
people would look
like her before picture on the left and
say i'm going to take the next two years
to just get as strong as possible
and try to stay the same weight on the
scale my guess is not that many most
people say i need to cut i need to
starve myself i need to do tons of
cardio
and i need to lose a bunch of weight but
sydney stuck it out she had patience
and she was rewarded look at the results
so i'll leave you with one final story
almost five years ago i turned 40 years
old and my birthday is july 26th but
right at the beginning of the new year
in january
i started planning a blog post for my
40th birthday
so i was 39 and a half and i'm like you
know what
i'm gonna spend the next six months
training hard as hell
making lifting my number one priority
you know
going for pr's making sure i'm well
rested i'm gonna make my workouts
numero uno it's instead of my business
or my social life so
i trained so hard during those six
months i set prs in every single lift
i stayed 238 pounds for six straight
months
my weight only varied four pounds
throughout the year
i originally was going to try to get
down to 225 pounds
which is what i weighed in 2015 when i
got really lean
but i was so hungry i was trying to be
on a deficit
and do more walking but i just couldn't
control my appetite you know i suffered
but i guess i didn't suffer too much
nevertheless i ended up looking way
better you know i knew i was going to
take pictures for my 40th birthday and i
was very proud of my look
this was before my grey beard hair set
in
my beard was majestic and i look like a
lumberjack you know
so there's no research that i'm aware of
indicating that bulking and cutting is a
superior strategy to recomping
it does have a good theoretical basis
especially when you get down to really
low body fat levels the problem is most
people never get to those really low
body fat levels they don't ever need to
bulk and cut
they can just recomp this is especially
important for people who don't like the
way they look while they're bulking
a lot of women i know they're like man i
hate this why do i have to be bulking
and
guys we tend to be better at accepting
the bulk
i can look in the mirror and i
completely ignore this area
my eyes don't even recognize this belly
i have here i will look in the mirror
and be like check out those packs
look at these traps look at that look at
those delt gains
look at these quads i knew early on i
was not most people
and i know that it's temporary i know
that i can lose this belly
in a few months but i don't know many
women that are like look at these trap
gains
look at trapzilla you know i wish more
women
just got as strong as possible and let
the chips fall where they may in terms
of physique my squad now they're so
strong and i love how athletic and
strong they look
i'm not in charge of their physiques
they are you know if they say to me i
don't like
my traps are getting too big for my
liking or my back is too big or
something
i hate it i hate having to cut out
deadlifts or something or
no more lateral raises or something
because i love what those exercises do
for other muscles as well
so in summary bulking is cool
cutting is cool recomping is cool use
the right
tool for the right job and just know
that recomping is a viable strategy i
think more people should do it
do you need to book and cut no you don't
you can recomp
all right that's a wrap if you liked the
video please make sure you give it a
thumbs up please make sure you hit like
make sure you're subscribed to my
channel i know i've been on a little
lull lately but i do plan to get back
into things regularly
and post one to two videos every week
i've been working very hard but
alex i don't know what happened to my
camera guy he just i think he had mono
for like three months
or something you long covered alex threw
a tantrum i'm sorry
we've been working on a certification
planning a documentary
filming content for bc strength
equipment and we've even been expanding
booty by brett
so my camera guy alex has been very busy
but a lot of that's cleared up so we
should be back in business
and feel free to leave a comment tell me
what you'd like to hear from me
i'm always open to new ideas for example
i always post about glutes but i know a
lot about the other muscles in the body
i know a lot about a lot of different
topics in strength and conditioning
i always try to serve my niche but i'm
thinking about branching out
all right thanks for watching
[Music]
if you like what you saw in this video
and you want to train under my system
and principles
then i invite you to click on the link
below and subscribe to booty by brett
and join the thousands of other happy
members who are seeing amazing results
[Music]
pages